Curriculum Vitae Rob van der Meij

Personal data

Address Prins Constantijnlaan 15

3818 ZH Amersfoort

the Netherlands

Phone +31-33 4620100 (home)

+31-6-46252145 (mobile)

Birth date April 1, 1965

Marital Status Married, 2 children

Summary

Experienced international general/business manager. Strong in customer/market orientation and business/strategy/technology development and deployment. People skills recognized and respected. High capability to develop and sustain international relationships. Global experience base having worked abroad (USA) and globally (intensive travel) in multinational companies with international strategic customers across the world and joint ventures (Japan, Brazil). Experience both in large companies (Shell, Akzo Nobel) and in entrepreneurial, venture capital funded startup companies (BIOeCON, KiOR, Hermes, fluXXion). Proven capability of quickly understanding new markets and businesses.

Education

University and post-academic

- 1983-1987 Chemical Engineering, Technical University of Delft
- 1993-1994 Industrial Marketing, Stichting Technical Marketing
- 1994-1996 Business Administration, Leergang Bedrijfskunde, Amsterdam
- 2009-current: Nyenrode Business University, New Board Program

In-Company training

- Akzo Nobel Management Development program
- Akzo Nobel Sr Management & Executive program (Theseus business school, France)
- A variety of internal and external training programs in finance, joint venture and alliance development and operations, sales (Miller Heiman), negotiation skills, economy courses , safety, diversity management, ISO etc.
- Cap Gemini Ernst & Young/Gemini Consulting training, various consulting skills, project management, change management workshops.
- IMD, Shell Global Business Leadership Program, senior executive level (IMD Lausanne, Switzerland)

Work experience

September 2009-current, CEO fluXXion BV

- Venture Capital funded start up that is already a start up for 5 years....requiring a turnaround
- Defined new strategy and new business plan around recent new development for application of fluXXion technology
- Driving technology partnering and commercialization of technology with large OEM/Technology providers such as Tetra Pak, Bayer etc
- Currently entering new fundraising round for commercialization phase of company. Exit target in 2 years.

July 2008-current, CEO/Founder Hermes Catalysts BV

- Start up/owner niche catalyst sales and development company (4 people)
- Develop outsources manufacturing and research & development relations in Europe and US
- Arranged representation Chinese Catalyst company in Europe/USA (new market entry), first sales to major oil companies made
- Start up trading activities to generate cash flow (FCC Equilibrium Catalysts, absorbents)
- Develop new niche products in cooperation with Dutch/Czech, US, Chinese and Japanese catalyst companies
- Developed catalyst supply position in Middle East with few million USD revenue
 now.

June 2007-June 2008, CEO/Founder KiOR Inc (Business Director BIOeCON)

- Joined BIOeCON as Business Director, arranged short term 'survival' finance, developed business plan and strategy to attract long term finance
- Negotiated and created venture capital for KiOR, joint venture between Khosla Ventures (leading US venture Capital firm) and BIOeCON
- Start Up CEO KiOR, created business and technology development plan, recruited startup team (15 people in 4 months), set up company in Houston, TX, USA
- Arranged second round financing for KiOR and hired successor CEO in Houston, TX
- Created KiOR-Petrobras cooperation agreement
- Developed spin-out strategy for other BIOeCON technologies (Chemicals, Ethanol)

Global Business Manager Derivatives , Shell Chemicals, 2004-2007

- P&L responsible for global Derivatives business in Shell Chemicals (supply of surfactants to the detergents industry). Direct reports are sales, marketing, strategy.
 Plant, supply & customer service operations indirect via functional organization
- Portfolio includes 7 manufacturing plants (US (2), UK (3), South Africa, New Zealand), revenue exceeding 1 billion USD, invested capital several hundred millions USD.
 Sales and Marketing operations in over 50 countries

General Manager Clean Fuels Technology, Shell/CRI-Criterion Catalysts and Technology (2002-2003)

Two main responsibilities:

- 1. Develop Technology Sales & Licensing business, jointly with Shell Global Solutions (World outside the US)
- 2. Develop Strategy, Integration & Business alignment between Criterion and Shell Global Solutions (strategy, concept and implementation)

This position was a new role in Criterion and was created to improve the strategic and operational alignment between CRI-Criterion and Shell, the Shell Global Solutions division in particular. CRI is the 'Shell' Catalyst Company, working both for internal and external clients (30/70 internal/external). Shell Global Solutions is the Shell technology and services company, working mainly internal, but with a growth ambition to external customers. This resulted in successful licensing business for Shell with CRI being fully integrated in Shell Gloval Solutions.

Managing Consultant, Cap Gemini Ernst & Young, Strategic Consulting (former Gemini Consulting) (2000-2001)

Role: Project management and business development

Strategic Consulting in CGE&Y focused on strategy implementation projects and especially the change processes and create a sustainable hand over to the client. Activities include strategy development, improvement and implementation.

- Project Manager for design and implementation of software maintenance and development department for eBusiness Competence Center at large, global consumer electronics company.
- Project Lead for Sales & Marketing at reorganization project of a business unit of a major global specialty chemicals company.
- Various business development activities (Pharma, Chemicals, Innovation, Value Creation)

Various positions at Akzo Nobel Catalysts (1987-2000)

1999-2000

General Business Manager Fluid Cracking Catalysts EUMEA (Amersfoort, the Netherlands)

- Responsible for sales, marketing, production and development activities for FCC EUMEA market area (greater Europe, India, Russia and CIS, Africa, Middle East).
 Operating Income and operational management responsibility for FCC EUMEA group with total revenue appr. \$100 million/year and appr. 150 people (manufacturing, R&D, sales & marketing).
- Managed global key accounts and marketing alignment with joint venture in Brazil and US operation

1998-1999

Business Manager Hydrocracking and Technology Licensing (Houston, TX, USA, Amersfoort, the Netherlands)

 Responsible for global P&L of Hydrocracking catalyst sales and technology licensing business and responsible to create and operate new global technology marketing and development alliance with 2 major oil companies (Fina and Mobil) and one major engineering company (Kellogg)

1996-1998

Sales Manager North America and Global Task Force Leader Hydrocracking and Technology Licensing (Houston, TX, USA)

- Sales management of Sales group) for North America, located in Houston, TX, USA. Responsible for net revenue and contribution margin for North American
 hydroprocessing catalyst sales (sales > 50 million USD/year).
- Global taskforce leader technology licensing & hydrocracking catalyst sales, responsible for strategy and business development

1987-1996, various operational level positions in Sales, Technical Service and Research and Development (Amsterdam and Amersfoort, the Netherlands)

- Area Sales Manager Sales Refinery Hydroprocessing Catalysts, responsible for sales in Scandinavia, East and Mid Europe, Mediterranean, Middle East, India, China, Russia, Baltics, Africa
- Applications Research & Development Manager Chemical and Custom made catalysts, manager for product and marketing development, new products market introduction and scale up from R&D to manufacturing,. Global market area, focus on Asia Pacific and North America.
- Section leader for Applications Research and product development manager
 Chemical and custom made catalysts,.
 - Developed new custom made product range for major Asian petrochemicals company to reduce its dependency on technology licensor
 - Solved major manufacturing problems for existing products by adapting product design
 - Developed several improved test methods for existing catalysts to show value for improved performance
 - Reduced cost of testing by developing more automated testing and analysis procedures

Other activities

- Invited speaker at Management Centre Europe for Joint Ventures and Alliances operations
- Invited speaker at Stichting Techniek and Marketing ("technical marketing") for "cultural issues in international business" and "pricing in industrial markets".
- Guest speaker at Berlitz for Dutch-American culture training class
- Organized both in Shell and Akzo Nobel several 'Technical Marketing & Sales Awareness' courses for technical and R&D staff

- Set up research project between CGE&Y and Stichting Techniek and Marketing to investigate how marketing can contribute to value capture in industrial markets
- Chairman and invited speaker at various international industry conferences.
- Member of works council Akzo Nobel Chemicals NL, 1995-1996.

Language

- Dutch and English fluent
- German speaking & reading good, writing fair
- French speaking, reading and writing fair